Guide to the Daniel Harvey Hill (1859 - 1924) Papers
Daniel Harvey Hill (1859 - 1924) Papers
1883-1955
1883 1955
Hill Daniel Harvey 1859-1924
MC 00022
The Daniel Harvey Hill (1859 - 1924) Papers, 1883 - 1955, contain items relating to Hill's career at North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts (later North Carolina State University) as an English professor, Vice President, and President. Many of the materials document Hill's professional career, particularly his appointment to and resignation from the presidency of the College. There are also manuscript drafts of texts Hill wrote on the Civil War and on his father, General D. H. Hill. A small number of personal materials are also included. The bulk of the materials date from 1908 to early 1920s.
Daniel Harvey Hill (1859-1924) was an educator, college president, writer, and historian. He received a B.A., M.A. and Doctor of Literature degree from Davidson College. In 1908 he became the third president of the North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts, where he served from 1908 to 1916.
1.25 linear feet
North Carolina State University Libraries, Special Collections Research Center
Gift of Randolph Isabel Hill, Accessions 1967.0006, 1969.0009, and 1970.0002 (1967-1970). Additional gifts made by North Carolina State University Office of Foundations and Development, Accession 1984.0003 (1984) and by Randye Finigan and Wendy Lawton, Accession 2013.0193 (2013).
The collection is organized into two principal series:The Personal Materials series is divided between correspondence and biography.The Professional Materials series contains three subseries, namely Correspondence, Collected Newspaper Articles, and Writings.
Daniel Harvey Hill, the second son of Confederate general Daniel Harvey Hill and Isabella Morrison, was born at Davidson, North Carolina, on 1859 January 15. In 1880, Hill graduated from Davidson College with a Bachelor of Arts degree; shortly thereafter, he began teaching as a professor of English at the Military and Agricultural College at Milledgeville, Georgia. During the nine years he taught at that institution, Hill married Pauline White of Milledgeville (1885) and received a Master of Arts degree from Davidson College (1886). He received a Doctor of Literature from Davidson in 1905 and a Doctor of Laws from the University of North Carolina in 1910.
Hill returned to North Carolina in 1889 when he was hired at the recently-established College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts (now North Carolina State University). For almost twenty years, he served as professor of English and bookkeeping, faculty secretary, and treasurer. In 1905 he was elected Vice-President, a position he fulfilled while remaining professor of English. Three years later, Hill became the third president of the College. He held that position for eight years, resigning in 1916 to write a history of North Carolina troops during the Civil War entitled Bethel to Sharpsburg (1926).
Hill's lengthy academic career was coupled with an equally extensive literary career. His interest in North Carolina history manifested itself in his book about the state in the Civil War for the twelve-volume Confederate Military History (1899). Collaborating with colleagues, he wrote the textbooks Young People's History of North Carolina (1907) and Agriculture for Beginners (1903); a series of five schoolbooks collectively known as Hill Readers (1906); and Corn Book for Young Folk (1920). Throughout the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, Hill served as editor of The Southern Home, a weekly newspaper that had been founded by his father.
Hill participated in numerous organizations, mostly those with a historical or literary focus, during his time at the College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts. He was a member of the North Carolina Historical Commission, the North Carolina Society of the Sons of the Revolution, United Sons of Confederate Veterans, and the Southern Educational Association. He was the president of the North Carolina Teachers Assembly, the North Carolina Folklore Society, and the North Carolina Literary and Historical Association. Hill also served as chairman of the state council of defense during World War I.
Following his retirement, Hill remained in Raleigh until poor health compelled him to relocate to the western mountains of the state. He died on 1924 July 31 at Blowing Rock, North Carolina, and was survived by his wife and five children.
Daniel Harvey Hill (1859 - 1924) Papers, P. C. 94, North Carolina State Archives, Raleigh
Daniel Harvey Hill (1821 - 1889) Papers (2035), Southern Historical Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
Daniel Harvey Hill (1821 - 1889) Diary (882), Southern Historical Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
Daniel Harvey Hill (1821 - 1889) Papers, North Carolina State Archives, Raleigh
This collection contains material relating to Daniel Harvey Hill and his career at North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts, where he held positions as English professor (1889-1908), Vice-President (1905-1908), and President (1908-1916). The collection contains personal correspondence, copies of a short pamphlet written by Hill on North Carolina history, and newspaper articles about Hill, his career, and the College more generally. Many of the materials document Hill's professional career, particularly his appointment to and resignation from the presidency of the College. There are also manuscript drafts of texts Hill wrote on the Civil War and on his father, General D. H. Hill. A small number of personal materials are also included. The bulk of the materials date from 1908 to early 1920s.
Hill D. H. Daniel Harvey 1821-1889; North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts--History; Hill Daniel Harvey 1859-1924; North Carolina State University--History; Hill Daniel Harvey 1859-1924; North Carolina Historians; Clippings; Letters (correspondence); History North Carolina 1865-; North Carolina College presidents; History North Carolina Civil War, 1861-1865
- Personal Materials, 1883 - 1920; 1883 1920
  This series contains two letters from Daniel Harvey Hill (probably the father, Confederate Lieutenant General Daniel Harvey Hill), one to Nannie Hill and a second to Joseph Hill. The folder includes typed transcriptions of both letters. Also included in this series is an undated biography of the father. Finally, the series has three portrait photographs of Daniel Harvey Hill (the son).
  - Letters, 1883, 1916 (Halfbox 1, Folder 1)
  - "Lt. Gen. Daniel Harvey Hill: Senior Soldier,", circa 1920 (Halfbox 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Circa 1900 (Legalbox 2, Folder 1)
- Professional Materials, 1901 - 1955; 1901 1955
  The Professional Materials series is divided into three subseries. The Correspondence subseries includes letters and telegrams Hill received in honor of his appointment to and resignation from the presidency at the North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts. The Collected Newspaper Articles and Addresses includes materials about Hill's career, specifically his resignation in 1916, as well as newspaper articles about the College's search in 1916 for a president, general College news from a 1924 Raleigh News and Observer, the 1955 dedication of D. H. Hill Library at North Carolina State College of Agriculture and Engineering (later North Carolina State University), and an undated [circa 1920] editorial. Also included are materials on General D. H. Hill and an ancestor named William Hill. The Writing subseries includes a pamphlet on North Carolina history published by Hill as well as his resignation letter to the Board of Trustees and former students of North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts. There are also manuscript drafts of texts Hill wrote on the Civil War and on his father, the general.
  - Correspondence, 1894 - 1916
    - 1894 April 16 (Legalbox 2, Folder 2)
    - 1908 July 23 - July 25 (Halfbox 1, Folder 3)
    - 1908 July 26 - September 29 (Halfbox 1, Folder 4)
    - 1915 December 31 - 1916 February 15 (Halfbox 1, Folder 5)
    - 1916 April 10 - May 22 (Halfbox 1, Folder 6)
    - 1916 May 23 - August 2 (Halfbox 1, Folder 7)
  - Collected Newspaper Articles and Addresses, 1916 - 1955, undated
    - Archer Anderson Address on General Daniel Harvey Hill, Undated (Legalbox 2, Folder 3)
    - Daniel Harvey Hill, 1916 - 1920 (Halfbox 1, Folder 8)
    - North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts, 1916 - 1955 (Halfbox 1, Folder 9)
    - William Hill Narrative of the 1770 Campaign in South Carolina under Thomas Sumter, Undated (Legalbox 2, Folder 4)
  - Writings, 1901 - Circa 1920
    - Life of General D. H. Hill (Handwritten Draft) (1 of 2), 1915 (Legalbox 2, Folder 5)
    - Life of General D. H. Hill (Handwritten Draft) (2 of 2), 1915 (Legalbox 2, Folder 6)
    - Life of General D. H. Hill (Typed Draft) (1 of 2) (Legalbox 2, Folder 7)
    - Life of General D. H. Hill (Typed Draft) (2 of 2) (Legalbox 2, Folder 8)
    - "The North Carolina Booklet: Greene's Retreat,", 1901 (Halfbox 1, Folder 10)
    - North Carolina in the Civil War, copy 1 (Typed Draft) (1 of 3) (Legalbox 2, Folder 9)
    - North Carolina in the Civil War, copy 1 (Typed Draft) (2 of 3) (Legalbox 2, Folder 10)
    - North Carolina in the Civil War, copy 1 (Typed Draft) (3 of 3) (Legalbox 2, Folder 11)
    - North Carolina in the Civil War, copy 2 (Typed Draft) (1 of 3) (Halfbox 3, Folder 1)
    - North Carolina in the Civil War, copy 2 (Typed Draft) (1 of 3) (Halfbox 3, Folder 2)
    - North Carolina in the Civil War, copy 2 (Typed Draft) (3 of 3) (Halfbox 3, Folder 3)
    - Pages Possibly from a Draft of the Life of General D. H. Hill (Halfbox 3, Folder 4)
    - Resignation Letters, 1916 (Halfbox 1, Folder 11)